Guide to the Theodore Hornberger Papers, 1930-1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Theodore Hornberger papers 1930-1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hornberger, Theodore, 1906-1975
1.4 linear feet Extent: 463 Items
Theodore Hornberger (1906-1975) was a professor of English and scholar of Puritanism and Colonial American literature. Papers contain lectures, drafts, printed material, reprints, manuscripts, and correspondence relating to Hornberger's work on Puritanism and colonial American literature. Included are bibliographies compiled by Hornberger on the subjects of Puritanism, science, literature, and education, lecture notes on a variety of topics and individuals in American literature and history, and a draft manuscript of his book Puritanism and Science.
RL.00601
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Theodore Hornberger Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1977 and 1982.
Biographical Note
>Theodore Hornberger (1906-1975) was a professor of English and scholar of Puritanism and Colonial American literature.
Collection Overview
The Theodore Hornberger Papers contain lectures, drafts, printed material, reprints, manuscripts, and correspondence relating to Hornberger's work on Puritanism and colonial American literature. Included are bibliographies compiled by Hornberger on the subjects of Puritanism, science, literature, and education, and lecture notes on a variety of topics and individuals in American literature and history.
Professor Theodore Hornberger, educator and professor emeritus at the Univeristy of Pennsylvania at the time of his death, had worked over many years on the manuscript of a book on Puritanism and science. Two earlier versions were submitted to publishers but owing to the shortage of paper and the economy of the world during World War II, they were never published. The bulk of Hornberger's papers consist of the third version of his Puritanism and Science in manuscript. He died before completing it.
Acquired as part of the Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography at Duke University.
Subject Headings
Hornberger, Theodore, 1906-1975; American literature -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775 -- History and criticism; American literature -- Study and teaching; Puritans; Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- Professional Papers Series, 1934-1976, (1 box)
  Contains material relating to Hornberger's professional career as professor of English at the University of Minnesota, the University of Texas, and the University of Pennsylvania. Also contains several clippings from the New York Review of Books.
  - Biography, 1964-1976 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1934-1937 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1968 (Box 1)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1963 and undated, (4 boxes)
  Largely consists of lectures and lecture notes on a variety of topics and individuals in American literature and history, such as Ralph Waldo Emerson, James Fenimore Cooper, Washington Irving, Cotton Mather, and John Winthrop. Also includes bibliographies Hornberger compiled on the subjects of Puritanism, science, literature, and education, fragments of Hornberger's writings, a manuscript of his book Puritanism and Science, reprints of articles by Hornberger and others, a copy of The Literature of the United States edited by Hornberger and two others, and handwritten notes.
  - Bibliographies (4 folders)
    - Puritanism and Education (Box 1)
    - Relations of Literature and Science, 1951-1953, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - Relation of Science to Philosophy, Religion, and Sociology (Box 1)
    - Writers of Puritan Prose (Box 1)
  - Cotton Mather Chapter 5 Fragments (Box 1)
  - "History of Science" Fragments (Box 1)
  - Lectures, (23 folders) (Box 1)
    - American Literature, 19th Century (Box 1)
    - Bradford, William (Box 1)
    - Bryant, William Cullen (Box 1)
    - Coles, Abraham (Box 1)
    - Colonial Literature, Belles Lettres (Box 1)
    - Cooper, James Fenimore (Box 1)
    - Emerson, Ralph Waldo (Box 1)
    - Fiske, John (Box 1)
    - Franklin, Benjamin, 1964, Contains 1 audio tape reel, 7 inch and transcription of lecture. (Box 1)
    - Frenau, Philip (Box 1)
    - Fuller, Henry B. (Box 1)
    - Hamilton, Alexander (Box 4)
    - Higginson, John (Box 1)
    - Irving, Washington (Box 1)
    - Mather, Cotton (Box 1)
    - Mather, Increase (Box 1)
    - Mayhew, Jonathan (Box 2)
    - Minor Writers (Wallir, Thomas; Warren, John; Warren, Joseph; Waterhouse, Benjamin) (Box 2)
    - Puritan Prose (Box 2)
    - Puritans (Box 2)
    - Travel Literature (Box 2)
    - Williams, Samuel (1743-1817) (Box 2)
    - Winthrop, John (Box 2)
    - Woolman, John (Box 2)
  - Walter Blair, Theodore Hornberger, Randall Stewart, eds. The Literature of the United States (Glenview: Scott, Foresman and Company, 1963) (Box 2)
  - Manuscript Fragments (Box 2)
  - "Mechanics" (Box 4)
  - Notebooks (Box 4)
  - Poetry, Indexes, and Notes (Box 2)
  - Puritanism and Science, (12 folders) (Box 2-4)
  - Reprints (Box 3)
  - Writings by Others (Box 3)